Guide to the Railroads and trolleys in the United States and Mexico: photographs, 1889-1972
Department of Special Collections
Railroads and trolleys in the United States and Mexico: photographs,
1889-1972
Mss Photo 201
2623 photographic prints (ca. 2,509 photographs and 3 albums with 114 photographs 2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Collection contains over 2,600 photographs documenting various railways and trolley lines in the United States (primarily California) and Mexico.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1999 and 2000.
Scope and Content
Photographs document electric railroad and street-railroad lines throughout the United States, primarily in California. Cars are identified for the following routes: Morgan's Louisiana & Texas Railroad, Pacific Electric Railway, Pennsylvania Railroad, Sacramento Northern Railroad, Santa Fe Railroad, Southern Pacific Railroad, Temiscouata Railroad, United Railroads and Union Pacific Railroad. Railway lines include: San Francisco Municipal Railway, California Street Cable Co., Market Street Railway, Sacramento City Lines, Stockton Electric Railway, Eureka Municipal Railway, Visalia Electric Railway, Marysville/Yuba City Railway, Interurban Electric Railway, San Francisco, Napa & Calistoga Railway, Los Angeles Traction Company, Los Angeles Interurban, Los Angeles Transit Lines, Los Angeles Pacific Railroad Co., Los Angeles Railway, Metropolitan Transit Authority Los Angeles, Central Ca. Traction Co., San Bernardino Valley Traction Co., Redlands Central Railway Co., San Diego Electric Railway and the Santa Barbara & Suburban Railway. Other lines include: Syracuse & Suburban Railway, Utah Idaho Central, New York Central and South Field Beach Railroad. Photographs taken in Mexico depict railroad engines, cars and trolleys and their route names.
Autographed captions on verso of many photographs identify railroad line, car identification number, builder, seat capacity and location. Several identify year that the train was built. The following names are stamped or written on verso of numerous photographs: Stuart A. Liebman, C. Savage, C.W. Jernstrom, Charles M.G. Johnson, Howard E. Johnston, D.L. Joslyn, J.W. Swanberg, A.C. Phelps, Jeffrey K. Winslow and George E. Votava
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Jernstrom, C.W.; Johnson, Charles M.G.; Johnston, Howard E.; Joslyn, D.L.; Liebman, Stuart A.; Phelps, A.C.; Savage, C.; Swanberg, J.W.; Votava, George E.; Winslow, Jeffrey K.; California Street Cable Railroad Company.; Central California Traction Company.; Central Pacific.; Claremont, University & Ferry Railway.; Claremont Railway.; East Bay St. Railways.; Eureka Municipal Railway.; Fresno Traction Company.; Frisco.; Interurban Electric Railway Company.; Kentucky Traction & Terminal Company.; Kitchner & Waterloo St. Railway.; Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority.; Los Angeles Interurban.; Los Angeles Pacific Railroad Company.; Los Angeles Railway.; Los Angeles Traction Company.; Los Angeles Transit Lines.; Market Street Cable Railway Company.; Marysville/Yuba City Railway.; Morgan's Louisiana and Texas Railroad and Steamship Company.; Nevada County Traction Company.; New York Central Railroad Company.; Northern Electric Railway.; Oakland, Antioch & Eastern Railroad.; Oakland Traction Company.; Ontario & San Antonio Hts. Railway Company.; Pacific Electric Railway Company.; Pennsylvania Railroad.; Philadelphia Transportation Company.; Point Loma Railroad Company.; Redlands Central Railway Company.; Sacramento City Lines.; Sacramento Northern Railway Company.; San Bernardino Valley Traction Company.; San Diego Electric Railway.; San Francisco Municipal Railway.; San Francisco, Napa & Calistoga Railway.; San Jose Railroad.; Santa Barbara & Suburban Railway.; Santa Fe Central Railway Company.; Shagit River Railroad.; Southern Pacific Company.; South Field Beach Railroad.; Stockton Electric Railway.; Syracuse & Suburban Railway.; Temiscouata Railroad.; Union Pacific Railroad Company.; United Railroads of San Francisco.; Utah Idaho Central.; Visalia Electric Railway.; Electric railroads -- Trains.; Local transit -- California.; Street-railroads -- Mexico -- 20th century.; Street-railroads -- United States -- 20th century.; Railroads -- California.; Railroads -- Mexico.; Transportation.; Trolley buses.; Photoprints. ftamc.
Collection Contents
- Morgan's Louisiana & Texas Railroad, 1890, 1 photo (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Northwestern Pacific Railroad, nd, 27 photos (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Sacramento Northern Railroad, nd, 44 photos (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Pennsylvania Railroad, nd, 2 photos (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Sacramento Northern, 1938-1955, 85 photos (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Southern Pacific Railroad, 1935-1940, 5 photos (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Southern Pacific Railroad, 1946-1952, 19 photos (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Southern Pacific Railroad, 1971, 61 photos (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Southern Pacific Railroad, 1972, 30 photos (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Southern Pacific Railroad, 1918-1948, 37 photos (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Southern Pacific Lines, nd, 117 photos (Box 1, Folder 11)
- United Railroads, nd, 36 photos (Box 1, Folder 12)
- San Francisco Municipal Railway, 1900-1958, 53 photos (Box 1, Folder 13)
- San Francisco Municipal Railway, (cable cars), nd, 152 photos (Box 1, Folder 14)
- California Street Cable Co., 1940, 36 photos (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Market Street Railway, 1938-1941, 47 photos (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Railways in and around San Francisco, 1939-1955, 22 photos (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Sacramento City Lines1936-1946 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Stockton Electric Railway (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Visalia Electric Railway (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Marysville/Yuba City Railway (Box 1, Folder 18)
- San Francisco, Napa & Calistoga Railway, 31 photos (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Temiscouata, 1948, 3 photos (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Los Angeles Traction Co. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Los Angeles Inter Urban (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Los Angeles Transit Lines (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Los Angeles Pacific Railroad Co., nd, 28 photos (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Railways in and around Los Angeles, 1889, nd, 30 photos (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Central California Traction Co. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- San Bernardino Valley Traction Co. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Redlands Central Railway Co., 1919-1940, 28 photos (Box 2, Folder 3)
- San Diego Electric Railway (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Santa Barbara Suburban Railway, nd, 37 photos (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Syracuse & Suburban Railway (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Utah Idaho Central (Box 2, Folder 5)
- New York Central (Box 2, Folder 5)
- South Field Beach Railway, 1933-1939, 6 photos (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Railroads, railways, unidentified, 1908-1947, 35 photos (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Railroad engines (Mexico), 1949-1962, 3 photos (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Railroad cars (Mexico), 1949-1957, 22 photos (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Trolleys (Mexico), 1949-1957, 39 photos (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Landscapes (Mexico), 1949, 9 photos (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Landscapes, San Francisco, ca. 1900-1948, 3 photos (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Railroads in Mexico (mini-album), nd, 16 photos (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Railroads in Mexico (album), nd, 70 photos (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Streetcars in Mexico (album), nd, 28 photos (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Pacific Electric, nd, 60 photos (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Pacific Electric, 8 of Pacific Electric stations, nd, 73 photos (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Pacific Electric (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Pacific Electric, nd, 42 photos (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Pacific Electric, nd, 34 photos (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Union Pacific Railroad, nd, 72 photos (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Santa Fe Railroad, nd, 53 photos (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Key System, nd, 63 photos (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Nevada County Traction Co. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Point Loma Railroad Co. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Oakland, Antioch & Eastern Railroad (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Oakland Traction Company (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Claremont, University, and Ferries horse cart (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Claremont Railway (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Eureka Municipal Railway (Box 3, Folder 8)
- East Bay Street Railways (Box 3, Folder 8)
- San Jose Railroad (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Skagit River Railroad (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Ontario & San Antonio Railway Co. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Kentucky Traction & Terminal Co. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Kitchner & Waterloo Street Railway, nd, 33 photos (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Petaluma & Santa Rosa Railway, 13 photos (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Los Angeles, 50 photos (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Metropolitan Transit Authority, nd, 24 photos (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Central Pacific, 10 photos (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Fresno Traction Co., nd, 3 photos (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Philadelphia Transportation Co.,nd, 2 photos (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Pacific Gas & Electric Co., nd, 7 photos (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Interurban Electric Co., 1939-1940, nd, 31 photos (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Northern Electric Railway, nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Frisco (Missouri), 1936-1947, nd, 6 photos (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Louisville & Nashville, 1953-1954, 2 photos (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Glendale & Montrose, nd, 2 photos (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Los Angeles & Pasadena Electric Railway, nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Los Angeles Cable Railway, nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 11)
- La Jolla Line Railway, nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 11)
- San Diego & Southwestern Railway, 1937, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Auburn & Northern Electric Railroad, nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 11)
- U.S. Mail - Highway Post Office, nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Elmira Water & Power, nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Everglades, nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Evanston Railway Co., nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Exter, Hampton & Amesbury Railway, nd, 2 photos (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Chicago, Burlington & Quincy (California Zephyr), 1953-1972, 2 photos (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Western Pacific, 1952-1953, 3 photos (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Springfield (Massachusetts) Street Railway, 1914, nd, 3 photos (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Berkeley Ferry (restored), 1981, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Unidentified Los Angeles trolley, nd, 1 photo (Box 3, Folder 12)